[QUENTIN]
Today we are going to discuss The Impact of AI on Ethical
Questions with Dr.
[QUENTIN]
Dorothy Bauer. She's an expert advising decision makers in tech
and finance on ethics, sustainability
[QUENTIN]
and responsibility. With this mix of academic and business
knowledge, she's advising companies and leaders
[QUENTIN]
to align financial goals and ethical values. Hi Dorothy, It's a
huge pleasure to have
[QUENTIN]
you today to discuss this very important question and actually of
the AI impact, but
[QUENTIN]
actually all, all the ethical question it raised and the ethical
problems that are implied
[QUENTIN]
by this current revolution that we are living. And I wanted to
start with this
[QUENTIN]
really this paper that has been discussed widely in the news and
in social media,
[QUENTIN]
published by Apple employees, called the Illusion of Thinking,
which basically point directly to one
[QUENTIN]
of your arguments that's overhyping AI is an ethical problem. And
I wanted to hear
[QUENTIN]
what you think about all this and what's your point about this
overhyping problem?
[DOROTHEA]
Hi Kanta, thanks for having me. Excited to be on this podcast.
And yes, the
[DOROTHEA]
Apple paper, like last weekend, suddenly everyone was talking
about it and I have to
[DOROTHEA]
disclaim first. I have not read it yet, but I have read its
reception mostly.
[DOROTHEA]
And so it's kind of taken very well or like very welcomed by
those who
[DOROTHEA]
have always said, wait, what Sam Altman and co are doing is they
are hyping
[DOROTHEA]
generative AI and they are ascribing it qualities that it doesn't
have. It will never
[DOROTHEA]
be able to really reason. And now the Apple paper seems to
confirm these criticisms
[DOROTHEA]
with the tests that they made. And for me, I'm looking at these
empirical discussions
[DOROTHEA]
between, you know, different schools of thought on, you know, how
to measure reasoning and
[DOROTHEA]
guys from different corners of machine learning, etc. Or like
more in favor of neurosymbolic
[DOROTHEA]
AI, etc. And I, you know, I can't judge the empirical aspects.
But as an
[DOROTHEA]
ethicist, what really interests me is like, would we want to have
AI that is
[DOROTHEA]
capable of reasoning? Why would we want to have that? And why are
the people
[DOROTHEA]
who are developing generative AI or like promoting the
transformer models? Why are they so
[DOROTHEA]
keen on making these promises? And that's what gets me started.
[QUENTIN]
So I guess the, the narrative or the argument will be that this
reasoning, if
[QUENTIN]
we can call it like this, but this step of thinking to solve
problems from
[QUENTIN]
some type of algorithm developed with, for example, reinforcement
learning might help to reach, to
[QUENTIN]
solve more complete complex problems. So I'm trying to avoid
being more intelligent, but it's,
[QUENTIN]
it's, it might help to solve more complex problem like with the
game of go,
[QUENTIN]
which was basically with this type of training, it's not
reasoning, but with this type
[QUENTIN]
of reinforcement learning that they achieved a level of go
player, virtual go player, higher
[QUENTIN]
than the best human. And I guess that's the idea is with this
kind of
[QUENTIN]
step by step solving of problem, we might be able to solve more
complex tasks.
[DOROTHEA]
It's very interesting to hear your perspective on that. Because
I'm more remote from the
[DOROTHEA]
field, you're more involved. And for me it's more like the
general feeling that they
[DOROTHEA]
are really obsessed with the idea that we need to beat humans and
that humans
[DOROTHEA]
are not good enough. So like, more. And I'm not a doomsday
prophet or anything,
[DOROTHEA]
but I'm more like, why are they so, you know, insistent on
arguing that, you
[DOROTHEA]
know, we need something that is better than humans and you are
taking it down
[DOROTHEA]
to a much more specific level, which is really helpful for me
because it also
[DOROTHEA]
kind of, you know, brings it back on the ground like, okay, yeah,
right, thanks
[DOROTHEA]
for reminding me that we do have some really complex problems to
solve and there
[DOROTHEA]
it might be helpful. But until now that I'm talking to you, the
messages I
[DOROTHEA]
get from OpenAI and Amodei, from Anthropic, et cetera is a much
bigger narrative of
[DOROTHEA]
humankind needs to be fundamentally changed, et cetera. And so
I'm really glad that you
[DOROTHEA]
reminded me of the thing. Yeah, we do have complex problems to
solve and if
[DOROTHEA]
AGI or whatever you want to call it, careful with this term can
help, that's
[DOROTHEA]
great. But even then, as you claim, you know, it can solve more
complex problems.
[DOROTHEA]
This, in my opinion, will only work when humans play along
because these, this AGI
[DOROTHEA]
or whatever, this reasoning AI will never be able or should never
be able to
[DOROTHEA]
act on its own. How do we get people to accept and cooperate if
there
[DOROTHEA]
is such a clear cut case where, okay, he I, whatever it is,
delivers a
[DOROTHEA]
solution or suggestion for solving a problem.
[QUENTIN]
Yeah, it's difficult indeed. I mean, we have to filter in to be
able to
[QUENTIN]
ask the right questions, to prompt well, even if it's evolving
and helping us sometimes
[QUENTIN]
to frame the right question, but it's most of the time. That was
the first
[QUENTIN]
podcast actually with Pitson, who is an expert on how to ask
questions and wrote
[QUENTIN]
an entire book on this. And this should really come from us, the
type of
[QUENTIN]
question we ask. But we definitely need to be able to filter out
and I
[QUENTIN]
mean to be able to judge. So we do need our human intelligence to
understand
[QUENTIN]
when there is something useful. When you have some Risks even if
we think about
[QUENTIN]
this type of general intelligence. But back to basically this
view and often the discussion
[QUENTIN]
mainly that I've seen recently by Sam Altman, for example, who
indeed seems that it's
[QUENTIN]
kind of creating this almost godlike creator. And I think one
thing that I thought
[QUENTIN]
also when you were speaking at the very beginning, I think a few
months after
[QUENTIN]
ChatGPT 3.5 release or March 2023, there was this
document signed by thousands of experts on AI to say we should
stop the progress.
[QUENTIN]
And I always felt that it, it sounds a bit like a marketing
campaign in
[QUENTIN]
the sense it's so good what we are doing that we, you have to
stop
[QUENTIN]
us. And I, I'm wondering if you, if you remember this and if what
you
[QUENTIN]
thought about it and what you think today about this type of
action is it.
[QUENTIN]
Is was it really genuine or was it more like a marketing trick?
[DOROTHEA]
Honestly, I struggle to believe that anything or a lot that comes
from, you know,
[DOROTHEA]
these circles is really genuine. It's. It's really hard to tell.
There are always like
[DOROTHEA]
overlapping groups. And I think the sign for the moratorium, I
think it was this.
[DOROTHEA]
There, there were people signing who are not aligned with Sam
Altman on other things.
[DOROTHEA]
And so it's, it's really difficult to, to keep track of who is
involved where
[DOROTHEA]
and who believes what. But I think in general hyping like, oh, we
will create
[DOROTHEA]
super intelligence next month as well as saying like stop it,
it's so dangerous. Both
[DOROTHEA]
is just feeding into the hype and it's not helpful. It's like
black or white.
[DOROTHEA]
And this like the. If Sam Altman even, or guys know that are like
related
[DOROTHEA]
to him or work on similar things, if they said, oh, we are so
good
[DOROTHEA]
now, you need to stop us. This is just, it's dishonest because
they have kind
[DOROTHEA]
of, they claim to have, you know, appropriated all the power to
create these things
[DOROTHEA]
and they put themselves in a position of those who are the only
ones capable
[DOROTHEA]
of keeping it under control. So it's like, you know, adopting a
really, an authority
[DOROTHEA]
that no one has ever given them that's never been legitimized.
Insane.
[QUENTIN]
Yeah, indeed. And the change, I mean, I'm pretty sure that's one
of the person
[QUENTIN]
who signed this document was also Elon Musk, who is today trying
to lead on
[QUENTIN]
the AI realm a few months, maybe one year later. So it's quite,
indeed surprising,
[QUENTIN]
this kind of opposite view.
[DOROTHEA]
Yeah. And even now. So Apple researchers from Apple have
published these, this paper, which
[DOROTHEA]
is another on a side Note, it's interesting that most of the
research comes from
[DOROTHEA]
companies now and there is hardly any independent university
research, which also, you know, must
[DOROTHEA]
make us a bit wary of like, you know, the interests involved. And
so, so,
[DOROTHEA]
so you could also say, oh, Apple, Apple is set to lag behind in
AI.
[DOROTHEA]
Maybe it's in their interest to publish something that says,
okay, it's not going to
[DOROTHEA]
work anyway, so. But I feel like a conspiracy theorist when I say
these things.
[DOROTHEA]
I'm not, I'm not. But the fact is that anything that happens in
AI is
[DOROTHEA]
so distinct from other fields of science, which are, as I said,
mostly, you know,
[DOROTHEA]
cultivated by universities. And now we're having companies with
billions of money, billionaires like Musk
[DOROTHEA]
and Bezos, et cetera, feeding this research, which is never free
from their own business
[DOROTHEA]
interests. And that's also something we need to take into
account. So whose agenda is
[DOROTHEA]
it? But again, I'm not talking about conspiracy theory. It's just
very different from, I
[DOROTHEA]
don't know, research in chemistry or in physics as we know it.
[QUENTIN]
We have seen during the inauguration of the second term of Donald
Trump, we have
[QUENTIN]
this row of top tech leaders just behind him and it set the tone
and
[QUENTIN]
on the role of tech leaders today and due to the sheer amount of
money
[QUENTIN]
they have, but also the impact they might have on society. And
also here I'm
[QUENTIN]
curious about your knowledge on ethical aspects of these
questions because it gives a lot
[QUENTIN]
massive power to private companies to shift, for example, or
shape the public opinion from
[QUENTIN]
managing the algorithm behind X, from Meta, but also on ChatGPT
because many people, hundreds
[QUENTIN]
of millions are using it probably daily. I'm not entirely sure
about the numbers, but
[QUENTIN]
a vast, basically set of people are using this daily. And you can
just shape
[QUENTIN]
the way the tool will answer. You can also play with the training
sets and
[QUENTIN]
erase some part of history if you would like to. You can also
push the
[QUENTIN]
opinion in very pervasive way in some direction. And I'm just
curious if this is
[QUENTIN]
also something you discuss or you see as a risk and how we should
deal
[QUENTIN]
with the fact that private company have today such an important
impact on society.
[DOROTHEA]
Yeah, it's certainly something to worry about because I mean,
ever since 1990s we've talked
[DOROTHEA]
about corporations as political actors in business ethics. And
now, now no one, now it's
[DOROTHEA]
not such a popular term anymore, but it seems to be just take for
granted.
[DOROTHEA]
It's, it's become normal. And of course they have a lot of power.
You know,
[DOROTHEA]
also the fact that they already have Billions and they're
spending billions directly into politics
[DOROTHEA]
and into elections, etc. That's like their first influence. And
then of course with things
[DOROTHEA]
like Starlink like Musk, he can switch off, you know, connection
wherever he wants. So
[DOROTHEA]
these are the obvious things. But then again, I think it's like
of course they
[DOROTHEA]
have most power, but everyone can use generative AI, especially
like large language models like
[DOROTHEA]
ChatGPT in order to try to manipulate people. We've had this
scandal recently with this
[DOROTHEA]
infamous study, unfortunately from University of Zurich, which is
nearby, where, you know, researchers tried
[DOROTHEA]
to undercover feed ChatGPT into Reddit, was it, I think
discussion threads and try to
[DOROTHEA]
convince people and change their opinion. So I think it's very
tempting for Anyone to
[DOROTHEA]
use ChatGPT to their own benefit. Of course the ones who created
it, they have
[DOROTHEA]
most power over it. But it's in general, it's a highly
manipulative tool in many
[DOROTHEA]
ways. For better or worse, you know, you can say I have a good
agenda.
[DOROTHEA]
It's okay, it's legitimate to try to convince people to be less
racist or whatever,
[DOROTHEA]
but it's a fact that everyone can use it however they like.
[QUENTIN]
Yeah, so that was exactly my reaction, I think actually in the
first podcast where
[QUENTIN]
we, I started with this paper I, I would say published in
Science, which showed
[QUENTIN]
that you could change the belief in conspiracy stories of people
on long term. It
[QUENTIN]
was really long, lasting at least a few months. What was meant by
long here
[QUENTIN]
and by discussing with these chatbots that were tuned to
basically help to shift the
[QUENTIN]
belief of people. And my first reaction was like, you could do
the opposite, right?
[QUENTIN]
Because it's very convincing, it's always available, it's
infinitely patient and it has this inherent
[QUENTIN]
way of basically being very convincing. And also because it has
been trained on correct
[QUENTIN]
answers, basically it was fed with this is a question, this is
the correct answer.
[QUENTIN]
So then basically these tools learned extensively to be
convincing and to pretend that they
[QUENTIN]
know. Not only because humans often are over optimistic, over
enthusiastic, heroic with their knowledge,
[QUENTIN]
but also because specifically in the training set and the way it
was trained, it
[QUENTIN]
was fed with a lot of correct answers by experts. So if you just
show
[QUENTIN]
this and as these tools are mimicking, and when I say this, it's
really LLMs
[QUENTIN]
are mimicking our behavior. They mostly observed people who were
confident of their answers. So
[QUENTIN]
then basically you have a lot of ways to reduce these issues and
they are
[QUENTIN]
work on this and they are trying to do this also with web search
and
[QUENTIN]
other techniques. But, but it tends to, to be very convincing.
And you see that
[QUENTIN]
indeed many people who are now exposed to this just take it for
granted because
[QUENTIN]
I know.
[DOROTHEA]
But some people think they're like the benevolent dictators that
never existed and they are
[DOROTHEA]
allowed because for good. And that's. It's just plain wrong. But
also what's striking, as
[DOROTHEA]
you say, I don't know. That's not something that he has ever
learned. And it
[DOROTHEA]
never, for example, has like the three dots for like thinking,
you know, it pretends
[DOROTHEA]
to think. It's like I'm thinking now, reasoning, but it's really.
And it's, it's annoying
[DOROTHEA]
because it's also been trained to be very, how they say,
sycophantic, like people pleasing,
[DOROTHEA]
et cetera. But that's why we in some situations prefer it over
people because other
[DOROTHEA]
people don't please us all the time. So. But these are
psychological issues. But you
[DOROTHEA]
know, what I find particularly striking about the fact that
these, like AI companies have
[DOROTHEA]
so much power is that at the same time they claim to be
democratizing something.
[DOROTHEA]
They say we're democratizing AI, et cetera. They are playing with
the word democracy when
[DOROTHEA]
they in fact are undermining democracy in so many ways.
[QUENTIN]
Will you say are the main ways they affect democracy?
[DOROTHEA]
Well, as we said, you know, be it by directly, you know, spending
money on
[DOROTHEA]
elections, like by trading government agencies that have never
been really legitimized by, you know,
[DOROTHEA]
training the algorithms and, you know, deciding who gets to
publish what on their social
[DOROTHEA]
media platforms by just making these tools available that, as we
just discussed, give anyone,
[DOROTHEA]
you know, huge opportunities to do their, to influence others,
etc. So in many, many
[DOROTHEA]
ways. But, yeah, so. But at the same time, we're democratizing
knowledge, we are democratizing
[DOROTHEA]
creativity, we are democratizing art, we're democratizing
education. What do you mean? You're just
[DOROTHEA]
commodifying things on a large scale. You're, you know, selling
your products. You're just talking
[DOROTHEA]
about access in terms of quantity and you're not thinking ahead
of what it really
[DOROTHEA]
means and on whose back. You're basically building up this axis
for others. So, yeah,
[DOROTHEA]
that's one of my pet peeves with the whole, you know, training
history of all
[DOROTHEA]
these models. Like, what were they trained on? Where did they
take that stuff from?
[DOROTHEA]
Who got compensated? Wait, no one. And so why do you call
democratization of art
[DOROTHEA]
now? When she stole it?
[QUENTIN]
Basically, yeah, this is you. No, no, but this is a very
important one. And
[QUENTIN]
there was this very good framing in a TED talk recently, but by
Ed Newton
[QUENTIN]
Rex on copyright Basically, and.
[DOROTHEA]
He says, one of my favorites.
[QUENTIN]
Yeah, it's very.
[DOROTHEA]
I haven't seen the TED Talk, but I really appreciate. Yeah.
[QUENTIN]
And the, basically the. So for the audience, the, basically the
pitch in the beginning
[QUENTIN]
of this, of this TED was these big AI companies, they have, they
require brains
[QUENTIN]
or engineers, a lot of data and a compute and they are ready to
spend
[QUENTIN]
hundreds of millions under engineers, sometimes billions on the
compute. So the computers. And for
[QUENTIN]
some reason for the third data, they expected to get it for free.
And you
[QUENTIN]
have this. Recently they said, I can't remember who said that,
but basically that they
[QUENTIN]
used hundreds, thousands of books under copyright because they
had no economic values. But if
[QUENTIN]
you used it because it.
[DOROTHEA]
Has a value for you, it's so cynical. It's so cynical. So Nick
Clegg, the
[DOROTHEA]
former British politician, then gone Meta executive, he recently
said, oh, if we had to
[DOROTHEA]
compensate all the authors for the work that we use to train our
AI models,
[DOROTHEA]
then the AI industry would go bankrupt. So I mean, I mean, how
dare you.
[DOROTHEA]
So does this legitimize it? And, and it's just, it's. I mean
really, I. That
[DOROTHEA]
Meta used this Russian pirate database, Libchen called
all, you know, millions and millions of books and texts to train
their llama. Their
[DOROTHEA]
model. And there was a piece in the Atlantic where you could
check whether on
[DOROTHEA]
that paratized database, you know, what works were in there. So I
entered my name
[DOROTHEA]
and I realized my thesis, every single article that I've ever
published is in that
[DOROTHEA]
database. So maybe I should feel flattered that maybe Meta used
my work. So finally
[DOROTHEA]
someone read it their LLM to feed their. Their AI. But it's just,
it's outrageous
[DOROTHEA]
what lengths they're willing to go to in order to, you know,
expand their power.
[DOROTHEA]
Unbelievable.
[QUENTIN]
It makes sense. For me at least now it feels that with everything
we are
[QUENTIN]
saying, I might understand why they want to pretend it's like
they are creating some
[QUENTIN]
superhuman intelligence. Because if it's for the greater good, if
it's for this big mission,
[QUENTIN]
you basically, it's.
[DOROTHEA]
A greater good to democratizing, universalizing, whatever agenda.
And then this is. Okay. And this
[DOROTHEA]
is just pure rhetoric. It's really, it's totally dishonest. Yeah.
[QUENTIN]
So it could be very provocative. It could be like some people who
use religion
[QUENTIN]
for this. Like, it's not me, it's God and it allows me to do
whatever
[QUENTIN]
and it's for the greater good, for humanity. And yeah, it's.
[DOROTHEA]
But it's also, you know, as we know, they don't even make money
off it
[DOROTHEA]
now of their LLMs, it's really hard to make money with them and
doesn't pay
[DOROTHEA]
off now. So a lot of that talk is also actually directed at
investors to
[DOROTHEA]
keep investors interested. So that's also one of the problems
when I said like research
[DOROTHEA]
is being done by the companies themselves. You know, a lot of the
research that's
[DOROTHEA]
published is trying to please investors. And you need to talk up
AI and make
[DOROTHEA]
AI sound better than it is. And at the same time what they also
do
[DOROTHEA]
is they talk down humans, they reduce us to computers. So they
say, oh, the
[DOROTHEA]
human brain is only just a computer anyway. We can easily copy it
so we
[DOROTHEA]
creating something better. So I think it's both ways. Talking up
the skills of AI
[DOROTHEA]
and playing down the skills or the complexity of humans. And it
goes together to,
[DOROTHEA]
to create this agenda that makes people think like oh, they are
our saviors, they're
[DOROTHEA]
working for a greater good.
[QUENTIN]
And even the terminology in AI might be problematic with that
respect because the fact
[QUENTIN]
that we use neurons. Exactly. Because it has in some way
initially the. The concept
[QUENTIN]
of mimicking the way our brain works. But we know that it's
widely different, it's
[QUENTIN]
extensively different. And all the terminology, I mean if you are
in statistics, it's not
[QUENTIN]
really exciting the terminology. It's really terms that are.
There is nothing fancy about this
[QUENTIN]
terminology, whatever. And in artificial intelligence it tends to
have really exciting terminology like already
[QUENTIN]
artificial intelligence neurons, deep neural networks and all
these things might also hides or makes
[QUENTIN]
us fantasize about what, what's behind this, this math. Because
these are just matrix, completion,
[QUENTIN]
multiplication. It's, it's really. But it's, it's, it's. Anyway,
even if you can reduce it
[QUENTIN]
to some mathematical operation, it's still very impressive what
it's capable of today. Even if
[QUENTIN]
it has cost and implication and issues. You also have some, some
very surprising effect
[QUENTIN]
and indeed I mean also related to ethical issues. I always seen
this situation as
[QUENTIN]
a world's natural experiment. It's really like we are not sure
what these tools are
[QUENTIN]
capable of, but play with them and here they are and we'll see
where it
[QUENTIN]
goes. And I feel that it's also. I don't know how it's viewed
from an
[QUENTIN]
ethical perspective from someone expert in this, but it feels
like there's, there's clearly some.
[QUENTIN]
It's a recipe for some dangers.
[DOROTHEA]
Let's say it is I think also what makes. I mean, and I must also
emphasize I appreciate AI. I appreciate, you know, it in all
kinds of forms. The
[DOROTHEA]
ones I Notice and actively use and the other ones that kind of
guide me,
[DOROTHEA]
you know, without me knowing it. I mean, I'm totally not anti AI
and you
[DOROTHEA]
know, really think there's a lot of good to be gained from it.
But as
[DOROTHEA]
you say, one of the problems in my eyes is also that we are
always
[DOROTHEA]
talking about general purpose AI. So that already says like,
okay, we created something that
[DOROTHEA]
channel purpose, so up to you what you use it for. So we are not
responsible for it. It's general purpose. You know, it's like
whether you use a hammer
[DOROTHEA]
to hit the nail or to kill someone, it's your responsibility. But
this channel purpose
[DOROTHEA]
also, like framework and, and rhetoric is really just escaping
accountability or like passing on
[DOROTHEA]
responsibility to those who use it. But imagine if maybe it's a
stupid comparison, but
[DOROTHEA]
if nuclear technology was general purpose and anyone could just
use it, you know, you
[DOROTHEA]
wouldn't. And of course I'm not comparing the direct dangers of
generative AI with nuclear
[DOROTHEA]
technology, but it's just like this general purpose mindset that
you're releasing something that's so
[DOROTHEA]
powerful under the label or with the frame general purpose should
not be ignored.
[QUENTIN]
So this leads also to this basically confusion that we have
today. So I was
[QUENTIN]
giving a talk recently to C Suites about AI and different type of
AI and
[QUENTIN]
I realized that for some people, even if I did my best to explain
what
[QUENTIN]
I was mentioning by AI, for some at the very end they thought
where can
[QUENTIN]
I use this predictive AI? Basically so things that we have been
doing for long
[QUENTIN]
time, decades in companies that these issues are working, they
all pictured basically AI as
[QUENTIN]
some kind of chatgpt with different functionalities. But it is
one specific type, right? It's
[QUENTIN]
really generative AI and large language models in particular. So
you mentioned this also, if
[QUENTIN]
I'm not mistaken several times, that this, that this also creates
issues when we are
[QUENTIN]
not clear about what we are discussing. Is it AI for prediction,
for forecasting in
[QUENTIN]
financial sector, for example, to detect and anticipate fraud, or
is it Genai, which is
[QUENTIN]
very different?
[DOROTHEA]
Yeah, it's in many ways it's really important that we separate
these because on the
[DOROTHEA]
one hand, just be aware that AI is more than just generative AI
and that
[DOROTHEA]
the ethical issues that are related to generative AI are
different from the ones like
[DOROTHEA]
risks and opportunities from the ones in predictive AI. But it's
this generative AI discourse
[DOROTHEA]
is just dominating everything. And I've also seen a CEO of one of
the big
[DOROTHEA]
four consulting companies in, in Switzerland, when he was asked
on a Panel like, so
[DOROTHEA]
how does AI play into your, you know, role as a CEO of this big
company? He said, oh, I, I have an LLM that helps me write emails
and
[DOROTHEA]
like, if this is like one of, you know, the big four, if this is
what comes into the mind of one of the CEOs, one of big four,
it's,
[DOROTHEA]
it's really a bit worrying. But I think also. So on the one hand
generative
[DOROTHEA]
AI has its problems as we have discussed its general purpose.
It's, it's, you know,
[DOROTHEA]
manipulative potential manipulative, potentially biased, can
also, you know, create access for people to tools
[DOROTHEA]
that they didn't have, etc. For the, you know, on a positive
note. But predictive
[DOROTHEA]
or AI for example, is single purpose. Often that's used for a
specific task. For
[DOROTHEA]
example, when it comes to climate science, you're predicting
weather events or analyzing, you know,
[DOROTHEA]
biodiversity, whatever, which is very helpful and which is hands
on and which is less
[DOROTHEA]
energy intense and which in the case of biodiversity doesn't hurt
anyone's privacy or data
[DOROTHEA]
hasn't been, you know, stolen mostly I hope. And so we're missing
all the opportunities.
[DOROTHEA]
So also for those who are like the doomsday profits when it comes
to AI,
[DOROTHEA]
they only focus on, on generative or like AGI promises, etc. But
there is a
[DOROTHEA]
lot of power like positive potential in AI, but maybe more so in
single purpose
[DOROTHEA]
AI where we specifically, you know, develop and use an AI to
application to, to
[DOROTHEA]
address specific problem in just of just instead of just, you
know, giving away the
[DOROTHEA]
general purpose AI and then see what happens. So I think in many
ways it's,
[DOROTHEA]
it's, it's, it's not good that this, this lopsided focus on
generative AI and also
[DOROTHEA]
I appreciate a lot. One of the best books I've read recently is
AI Snake
[DOROTHEA]
from Arvind Narayanan and Kapoor where they show so many use
cases. Of course they
[DOROTHEA]
look at them from a critical perspective. But that's also
important on, you know, what
[DOROTHEA]
can you really predict from data? How can human behavior be
predicted? What is possible,
[DOROTHEA]
what is not possible? Where can we rely on, you know, machine
learning or AI
[DOROTHEA]
to help us and where are the boundaries and this. All these
aspects get bypassed
[DOROTHEA]
by everyone talking about their latest prompts.
[QUENTIN]
It's true that while you are saying this, I could have this image
of how
[QUENTIN]
everybody was shocked and how it was relayed and everybody tried
and also because it
[QUENTIN]
was accessible, I guess. But with ChatGPT 3.5 everybody was
amazed that it could write
[QUENTIN]
Some kind of poems. For example, quickly, while you had AI before
helping to save
[QUENTIN]
lives, for example, by helping to detect tumor with MRI scan.
[DOROTHEA]
Exactly.
[QUENTIN]
And this is like not so, so popular or so well known by many
people.
[QUENTIN]
So.
[DOROTHEA]
But even then, for example, when it comes to, you know, image
recognition, radiology, etc.
[DOROTHEA]
It's so important to use AI in that context. But then you have
the people
[DOROTHEA]
who immediately claim we will not need radiologists anymore. They
immediately impose themselves on people
[DOROTHEA]
and. Or like, yeah. Then they claim they want to do away with the
humans,
[DOROTHEA]
which then triggers all the critics who focus on the cases where
AI has not
[DOROTHEA]
recognized the tumor instead of combining the two, you know,
okay, so we have AI
[DOROTHEA]
that can help us with image recognition in medical settings, but
we still need humans.
[DOROTHEA]
That's clear. Because all the benchmarks that they create to
measure how well an AI
[DOROTHEA]
performs in radiology are totally taken out of context. They are
not applicable to the
[DOROTHEA]
everyday work of radiologists anyway. But it's, it's like such a
talk, sorry, toxic culture.
[DOROTHEA]
So the ones say, oh, we have AI now, go away radiologists, we
don't need
[DOROTHEA]
you anymore. And the others who say, like, it should never be
used, it must
[DOROTHEA]
never be used, etc. It's too dangerous. And why can't you see it
as a
[DOROTHEA]
complementary relation? So it's really striking.
[QUENTIN]
Yeah. They are rarely the case that. So in some situations,
automation most of the
[QUENTIN]
time might be augmentation. Indeed. I mean, that's one of the,
the, the type of
[QUENTIN]
post I see the most on LinkedIn that is driving me crazy is reap.
And
[QUENTIN]
you say some kind of, of work, like rest in peace. Legal.
[DOROTHEA]
Yeah. Oh, okay.
[QUENTIN]
Developers.
[DOROTHEA]
Yes.
[QUENTIN]
And you're like, well, you know, so far it's not what we are
seeing. It's
[QUENTIN]
helping to augment if you do it well. But sure, there are some
job destruction.
[QUENTIN]
I mean, you.
[DOROTHEA]
Yeah, sure, but that's what I'm saying. Why do they feel so
obsessed with playing
[DOROTHEA]
up or talking up the skills of AI and playing down the skills of
humans?
[DOROTHEA]
Why, why is it, why can't you just say, hey, we have a helpful
tool
[DOROTHEA]
here, humans, you can do your jobs better. And of course some
jobs will, you
[DOROTHEA]
know, be become obsolete as always in history. But there's like
either the machine or
[DOROTHEA]
the human. It's just not helpful.
[QUENTIN]
But interestingly, I see some people who start to realize the
value of humans due
[QUENTIN]
to this substitution that some people are pushing and they're
like, actually, I really like
[QUENTIN]
to exchange with a human to learn from A new human to be in a
room with a physical person with their limitations, physical
experience of the world and emotions
[QUENTIN]
and suddenly we realize that this or we some people, it helps
them to realize
[QUENTIN]
that actually the all the uniqueness and valuable things that
humans have to offer. But
[QUENTIN]
indeed on the other hand of the spectrum, I guess you have other
people who
[QUENTIN]
for some reason would like to automate, replace everything and
does this doesn't seem to
[QUENTIN]
have any answer. What, what will be then the place of humans in
this society.
[QUENTIN]
Which is, which is peculiar.
[DOROTHEA]
Yeah. Yes.
[QUENTIN]
So when, when you go and talk to leaders in the business world,
how do
[QUENTIN]
you see that this hype. How do you deal with this hype and
basically help
[QUENTIN]
them to basically see it where, how they should see it or what
are the
[QUENTIN]
implication you. You see from this hyping of AI in the business
world with leaders?
[DOROTHEA]
Well, I mean I'm mostly you know, teaching in continuing
education like for example AI
[DOROTHEA]
and ethics in a, in a class on AI and finance. So there for
example
[DOROTHEA]
I developed a credit worthiness game with algorithms and, and I
played with different notions
[DOROTHEA]
of fairness just to show them the implications. If you think like
you have an
[DOROTHEA]
algorithm that's deciding who gets a credit and who does not. And
then I kind
[DOROTHEA]
of play around with like the, the normative or like. Yeah,
normative like moral assumptions
[DOROTHEA]
that are underlying different conceptions of fairness. So I
always keep it on a very
[DOROTHEA]
appl in my teaching and in my keynotes. Yeah, it's mostly kind of
tongue in
[DOROTHEA]
cheek also like showing that this is what's possible and wait
here there's something here.
[DOROTHEA]
I'm always ending with a strong plea for the human element must
be kept in
[DOROTHEA]
loop. But of course, I mean with people who are like totally
determined to hype
[DOROTHEA]
something or who have also as I say skin skin in the game, like
you
[DOROTHEA]
know, why would I want to ruin their dreams? But they don't get
in touch
[DOROTHEA]
with me anyway. So that's you know, not meeting those too often.
But yeah, in
[DOROTHEA]
continuing education you have people from different companies and
you can see, you know, different
[DOROTHEA]
levels of literacy. And I just always work with cases and case
studies and games
[DOROTHEA]
etc. To kind of reduce the distance between them and the
algorithm to see, you
[DOROTHEA]
know, what happens when you use AI in such and such setting.
[QUENTIN]
I see, I see. Yeah, interesting. And then indeed I've read some
research also to
[QUENTIN]
try to see when you don't you let just these also Gen AI tool
play
[QUENTIN]
traditional games we used in sociology and economics to see what
are Their traits, basically
[QUENTIN]
their behavior. And it was rather interesting to see their
standard answer and what it
[QUENTIN]
has learned basically. And of course you can tweak it, but it's
interesting to see
[QUENTIN]
already the same standard answer. And based as you discussed
about teaching, that's also a
[QUENTIN]
huge topic. I mean I have also many students every year and young
professionals and,
[QUENTIN]
and I mean it's, it has serious impact on the way people learn.
But also
[QUENTIN]
mainly something I wanted to discuss with you about this
basically democratization, inequalities and the
[QUENTIN]
fact that you, you have some research showing well in these
developing countries where it's
[QUENTIN]
hard to have the resources, we can automatize the teacher or
augment the teacher or
[QUENTIN]
replace the teacher entirely with an AI tool. It might help to
give access to
[QUENTIN]
education to many people. And in this discussion as well as in
other topics like
[QUENTIN]
mental health, I'm always. I see the benefits because I see some
research that I
[QUENTIN]
find convincing where I see that it can help if it's well made
and well
[QUENTIN]
done. But in other situation I'm a bit also afraid that then we
might say
[QUENTIN]
to the poorer you'll get the AI and to the richer you'll get the
real
[QUENTIN]
experts who can afford a human. Exactly.
[DOROTHEA]
Same doctors. You know, if you don't have a doctor in your
village and you
[DOROTHEA]
have AI based medicine, of course it's like better than nothing.
But. Yeah, yeah. But
[DOROTHEA]
I must say I'm careful with the whole education context because
I'm only a guest
[DOROTHEA]
lecturer. Luckily at universities I'm not involved in exams so I
can't really say anything
[DOROTHEA]
or I'm lucky not to have to deal with the fact how do we make
meaningful exams when everyone is using ChatGPT, etc. And, and,
and the psychological questions about
[DOROTHEA]
mental health is also something that yeah, I'm not really
qualified to say but as
[DOROTHEA]
you say like the value of the human and as you said before, it's,
it's
[DOROTHEA]
a paradoxical effect that the more we get to see AI, maybe the
more distinctive
[DOROTHEA]
is the value of the human interaction that we still have. But as
to for
[DOROTHEA]
example democratizing access to education, I mean the first thing
is you have public libraries,
[DOROTHEA]
create public libraries. You don't need an AI generated teaching
assistant, whatever.
[DOROTHEA]
Why does it always take AI?
I think it's taking me too far. We can start with other things
like people
[DOROTHEA]
need to have access to books and to also information, not just on
TikTok or
[DOROTHEA]
on social media. And that's where we need to start before we
start thinking about
[DOROTHEA]
creating A specific AI teacher for some remote regions of the
world.
[QUENTIN]
And indeed so some people, I suspect might react when they here
today, somebody mentioning
[QUENTIN]
a library that's, well, you have a lot of. It's not efficient.
You have to
[QUENTIN]
go there, you have to look yourself within something. You have to
open a book,
[QUENTIN]
find the right pages. The thing is with learning, and I was also
doing this
[QUENTIN]
episode on the podcast with MIT Prof. Who is focused on exactly
these questions we
[QUENTIN]
were discussing. And he was raising the point that you need some
friction to learn.
[QUENTIN]
You need those basic. You cannot accelerate everything. You have
to spend time and wrestle
[QUENTIN]
with the thing and actually maybe looking for a page, seeing
something is other book
[QUENTIN]
chapters that you didn't expect expose you to new things, make
you learn better and
[QUENTIN]
basically acquire better knowledge. And he did this very nice
experiment where he gave to
[QUENTIN]
his students to solve a problem. ChatGPT other has a low, lower
level. It was
[QUENTIN]
code llama, basically lower level AI Other has traditional,
traditional resources. Everybody could solve the
[QUENTIN]
task. The one with ChatGPT the fastest. And the day after he, he
said this
[QUENTIN]
in the beginning, you'll have an exam on this topic tomorrow. And
the one who
[QUENTIN]
used ChatGPT had the worst grade. And because basically they
could, even if they knew
[QUENTIN]
they, they will have an exam, it's because they took these
shortcuts and they could
[QUENTIN]
not compensate with these tools to properly learn. So these
things in the physical world
[QUENTIN]
are in more traditional ways of learning, are very useful.
[DOROTHEA]
You need to go through the process. I just quote from a blog
article from
[DOROTHEA]
Nicholas Carr that I read recently on like the myth of automated
learning, you cannot
[DOROTHEA]
automate learning. So he says AI is used by high school and
college students to
[DOROTHEA]
complete written assignments to ease or avoid the work of reading
and writing. Puts the
[DOROTHEA]
process of deskilling at education's core. To automate learning
is to subvert learning. It's a
[DOROTHEA]
brilliant piece. I mean, I wish I could read it from A to Z now,
here, because the way he nails it, you cannot delegate learning,
you cannot outsource learning,
[DOROTHEA]
you cannot automate it. If you haven't done it yourself and your
brain has understood
[DOROTHEA]
the whole thing, you're not going to know it. And that's why also
when you
[DOROTHEA]
know generative AI came first, it was like, now everyone can be a
writer, everyone
[DOROTHEA]
can be a photographer or an artist or a composer, etc. But. And
it was
[DOROTHEA]
seen as creating more equality. But it's different. Like those
people who have already been
[DOROTHEA]
authors, they become even better because they already know, you
know, they know their skills
[DOROTHEA]
and they can use it to become even better. But people who have
never written
[DOROTHEA]
a text, who don't know what a good text is, they won't be able to
judge the output that the AI serves them. And the same with
pictures. I mean,
[DOROTHEA]
I will not become an artist just because suddenly I would have
access to a
[DOROTHEA]
Danny whatever because I don't know art. So in the end it's like
keeping those
[DOROTHEA]
who have never learned the skills and if they're never taught the
skills anymore, because
[DOROTHEA]
we don't invest into human teachers and into the process of
acquiring skills, it keeps
[DOROTHEA]
them further away and it blocks them from entering the whole
world of art or,
[DOROTHEA]
you know, writing etc, Whereas those who had already, who had the
skills already, the
[DOROTHEA]
moment that generative AI popped up, they're just moving further
ahead and it's really driving
[DOROTHEA]
people apart.
[QUENTIN]
Yeah. So that's really something that I fear with my students.
Indeed it's seeing this,
[QUENTIN]
I mean, if I've learned to code and I used to do it for the
last 20 years, I can now benefit from these tools because I can
code faster.
[QUENTIN]
Just reread, check, adapt quickly. But then it's very hard to
learn if you already
[QUENTIN]
start with this. And same with many skills. I mean my. So
somebody told me
[QUENTIN]
recently that they were writing an email in front of maybe
someone who were 20
[QUENTIN]
years old something and he was surprised. The person was like,
but do you still
[QUENTIN]
write email yourself?
And others will say what's that? I've heard many, many times
these days. Also, why
[QUENTIN]
do you use Google? What? What's the purpose of using Google? It's
really interesting because
[QUENTIN]
it, it shows how fast the world changed and indeed it, it raised
many questions
[QUENTIN]
on. On what? And that's really my perspective today when I teach
because I spend
[QUENTIN]
a lot of time I was doing experimenting but also using AI and
hopefully in
[QUENTIN]
some way that I, I can indeed augment my capacity and not reduce
it. Also
[QUENTIN]
with learning, when I use specific tools like NotebookLM to just
interact with the content
[QUENTIN]
in an efficient way, but still using it like a tutor or a
sparring partner
[QUENTIN]
to acquire the knowledge rather than spitting the answers. And
the thing is, what I
[QUENTIN]
always share is as every time when I use AI, I try to do it
consciously. I know that I might gain some productivity time, at
least on the short
[QUENTIN]
run. But almost inevitably I will lose something.
[DOROTHEA]
Yes.
[QUENTIN]
And I have to accept this and make the conscious decision, okay,
I'm ready to
[QUENTIN]
lose on the learning capacity on this to gain a bit time to focus
on
[QUENTIN]
something that I give more value but. But this trade off is not
always clear
[QUENTIN]
to everyone and I think it's important to take this into account
before interacting.
[DOROTHEA]
Yeah, I think it's a big advantage of those who know both worlds
because we
[DOROTHEA]
can compare. We see what we gain, we see what we lose. But there
is
[DOROTHEA]
also this famous saying like every augmentation is an amputation.
I think it just applies,
[DOROTHEA]
you know, I mean like when you simple things if you only use
Google Maps
[DOROTHEA]
you're not able to read a map anymore, you know how you navigate
etc. And
[DOROTHEA]
this also applies here just that there is more at stake than just
reading a
[DOROTHEA]
map or using Google Maps. There is what is at stake is like as we
said, like the way of like proper thinking and acquiring
knowledge etc. That's what's at
[DOROTHEA]
stake. So that's. Yeah, but that's why I'm really glad I'm not
involved in. Not
[DOROTHEA]
full time involved in universities et cetera because these
questions are really tough to handle.
[QUENTIN]
They're very hard. Constantly discuss how to evaluate how to
teach. I constantly try in
[QUENTIN]
every class now I teach basically generative AI because it's.
People are using it so
[QUENTIN]
so that's. Anyway yeah try to help it Was this the also the
starting point
[QUENTIN]
with the episode on mental health? The person who created an app
specialized to support
[QUENTIN]
mental health in the university basically based on gen AI he said
well basically one
[QUENTIN]
of and it was a result from a recent research survey. The first
way people
[QUENTIN]
use these gen AI tools recently has been for companionship and
mental health support. So
[QUENTIN]
in a way basically people use it for this. So let's at least give
an
[QUENTIN]
obvious choice that is adequate or at least to the best extent
has some safeguards
[QUENTIN]
and can tweak, push help bring something to the table redirect
people to specialist humans
[QUENTIN]
specialists and and still try to take the advantages from these
tools. For example, in
[QUENTIN]
this the case of mental health we were discussing what happens if
it's 2am and
[QUENTIN]
you cannot reach to anyone and it's just to. You are in a
stressful situation
[QUENTIN]
and you have an adequate tool that can help you with the right
training to
[QUENTIN]
reduce the. The. The mental loads and redirect to. To. To the.
The professional. So
[QUENTIN]
in some situation it can definitely at least I think help if you
take the
[QUENTIN]
advantages. But we have to be very clear that we almost always
lose something.
[DOROTHEA]
Yeah, we do, we do.
[QUENTIN]
So we discuss very quickly about something but again maybe I'm
not sure
[QUENTIN]
how much time you spent discussing and thinking about this. But
about the copyright, which
[QUENTIN]
is very close to the. The ethical questions, right?
[DOROTHEA]
Yes.
[QUENTIN]
We have this basically Ghibli Giblification, and it was something
very dear to my heart
[QUENTIN]
because I was a big, big fan of Ghibli and I grew up with these
movies. And some people were telling me, well, you know, it's,
it's. It's doing some
[QUENTIN]
advertising, some marketing for AO Miyazaki, because I didn't
know him.
[DOROTHEA]
Before, and not what he wants, not the type of advertising he
wishes.
[QUENTIN]
Yeah, exactly. So that was first, also my, my reaction. Second
the second, I was
[QUENTIN]
always also telling these people. So at point taken. Let's say
for Ayao Miyazaki, it's
[QUENTIN]
some kind of advertisements. It increased the number of people
who watch these movies. Recently
[QUENTIN]
I convinced that he would and probably hated it. But let's not
think that I
[QUENTIN]
know the answer. But for all the other artists where you cannot
identify the art,
[QUENTIN]
it's not helping. And this is the vast majority. So you're
already helping the people
[QUENTIN]
on top. So. Yeah, I don't know what you think about this could be
the
[QUENTIN]
fix.
[DOROTHEA]
Yeah. No, no, no, no, no, no. Please don't expect the solution
from me. Just
[DOROTHEA]
today I'm submitting an article for a Swiss art magazine on, on
AI and art
[DOROTHEA]
and copyright and democratization of art, etc. Because I gave a
keynote last year at
[DOROTHEA]
the Institute for Intellectual Property in Switzerland on AI,
creativity and ethics. And so they
[DOROTHEA]
liked it. They said, oh, can we have that, you know, kind of an
article
[DOROTHEA]
on We Need Beer magazine? And we, we want to hear your voice in
the
[DOROTHEA]
magazine. So. Because there, you know, copyright is a, is a, is a
very legal
[DOROTHEA]
issue where. No, I'm not a lawyer. That's the first thing to say.
But the
[DOROTHEA]
thing is that
as we mentioned before, they have stolen everything, all the
works that they could find,
[DOROTHEA]
whether in violation of copyright or just like in violation of
moral decency. That's another
[DOROTHEA]
question. And then now they're creating tools that are actually
designed in the most cases,
[DOROTHEA]
to actively hide the authority. They're designed to hide the
author. They're designed to avoid
[DOROTHEA]
attribution, they're designed to avoid having to compensate. So
in the Ghibli case, it was
[DOROTHEA]
like in your face, straightforward plagiarism that they were able
to train, like, copy this
[DOROTHEA]
style, which is an exception because usually what we get is like
actively try not
[DOROTHEA]
to look, plagiarize too much and dissolve all the traces of the
individual creativity that
[DOROTHEA]
you have been trained on. And that's the very, very unfair. So
and, and compensation
[DOROTHEA]
models. I don't know if, if I hope that there are so many now,
there
[DOROTHEA]
are so many court cases going on against this practice. I hope
that there will
[DOROTHEA]
be some verdicts where companies are paid, at least in hindsight
or forced to pay
[DOROTHEA]
in hindsight to the creators whose works they have taken. But
it's. It's like after
[DOROTHEA]
the fact, first they stole it and now you know, you cannot undo
the theft.
[DOROTHEA]
It's impossible.
[QUENTIN]
Yeah, indeed. It's already this. And even if you want to,
basically there is this
[QUENTIN]
very important topic and very technical one which is called
machine unlearning. So it's basically
[QUENTIN]
you try to make the machine forget something, it learns, but it's
very hard because
[QUENTIN]
typically with cutting edge models where you have more than 1
trillion parameters, it's very
[QUENTIN]
hard to understand where this is embedded, what's it learned and
to make it forget.
[QUENTIN]
So it's a huge topic now in the engineering basically world, it's
like a.
[DOROTHEA]
Data leakage, privacy, you cannot undo it. It's out there. And
now everything has been
[DOROTHEA]
fed into these models. And now after this has been done, you want
to change
[DOROTHEA]
the reality. It's not possible.
[QUENTIN]
So one thing that I wanted to note that I really appreciate while
talking to
[QUENTIN]
you, which also highlight the difference with ll, is that
several, several times you note
[QUENTIN]
exactly where is your expertise and when you don't want to go,
I'm not a
[QUENTIN]
lawyer, I'm not lawyer.
[DOROTHEA]
I haven't read the paper, I'm not a lawyer, I'm not a machine
learning expert.
[DOROTHEA]
Yeah, I know my boundaries, thanks.
[QUENTIN]
But that's usually. Interestingly, that's something I discuss a
lot over the years. But I
[QUENTIN]
always see people and perceive people more highly instead of the
opposite when I hear
[QUENTIN]
that they openly share their limitations, the things they don't
know because we don't know
[QUENTIN]
everything. And the fact that you're able to know your boundaries
and also to say
[QUENTIN]
it out loud shows that you know that you don't know and your ego
is
[QUENTIN]
not too big such that you're able to say it loudly. Well, this I
don't
[QUENTIN]
know. I let it to the expert to judge. I might have an opinion.
[DOROTHEA]
But no, thanks for mentioning that. And I'm always. I also care
about attribution. You
[DOROTHEA]
know, I want to say where I learned something from because that's
helpful for other
[DOROTHEA]
people to know. I want to say I'm reading from this blog now. I
say,
[DOROTHEA]
you know, I'm reading AI Snake Oil because that's also what
differentiates me from an
[DOROTHEA]
LLM unless it's rag and it's correct. But you know, I said like,
hey, I
[DOROTHEA]
read this in that book. Maybe you want to read that book as well
or
[DOROTHEA]
read that blog piece. And that's what makes us humans. We learn
from humans. And
[DOROTHEA]
I think it's it really. Every single blog piece or article that I
read online
[DOROTHEA]
stays. So much brains ceremons I get from ChatGPT. Even if I only
want to
[DOROTHEA]
know, you know, something brief, it doesn't stick because there
is no human author behind
[DOROTHEA]
it. And I really think there is a difference in reception. When I
read a
[DOROTHEA]
carefully crafted blog post or book book written by humans, it
stays because there is
[DOROTHEA]
a history, there's a story, there's an author, there is
experience behind it. Whereas whatever
[DOROTHEA]
vomit comes through chat on the screen, it's just, you know, I
say stochastic, not
[DOROTHEA]
stochastic gambling. Yeah. Which is plausible, but there's no
authenticity.
[QUENTIN]
Yeah, I really like this, this point about indeed you connect
better due to the
[QUENTIN]
history behind it. Really also relate to the many discussion I
had about art where
[QUENTIN]
people were telling me well, but if you see a piece of art and
you
[QUENTIN]
cannot say that it's AI generated and you find it beautiful,
would it be really
[QUENTIN]
different that if it's made by a human? It is. It is.
[DOROTHEA]
Imagine you read, you read a great book, your favorite novel, and
then you notice
[DOROTHEA]
it has been written by Claude. You will be so disappointed
because you had ideas
[DOROTHEA]
in your mind about the author while you were reading it. You were
creating, you
[DOROTHEA]
know, assumptions, you know, explicitly or implicitly, and then
you find out there is no
[DOROTHEA]
author behind it. There is no story. It's. It's frustrating,
it's. It's disillusioning. It's. I
[DOROTHEA]
call it the disenchantment of, of art through AI.
[QUENTIN]
No. So I 100% agree. Some people disagree and I had many debate
about this,
[QUENTIN]
but it's a very interesting debate. But it feels that I have been
discussing with
[QUENTIN]
you for five minutes and I see that the time is moving.
[DOROTHEA]
Yes, it's running.
[QUENTIN]
There is a huge topic I wanted to discuss which is the impact on
sustainability
[QUENTIN]
and environmental questions. And I'm very curious because so far
I failed to find someone
[QUENTIN]
to come on the podcast and discuss this. It's a very tough one.
So I've
[QUENTIN]
been also working on sustainability before moving away from
academia and measuring environmental impact is
[QUENTIN]
difficult for many reasons. But first I'm curious about what your
view on this in
[QUENTIN]
light, for example, of this recent estimation, which is what it's
worth from Sam Altman
[QUENTIN]
on his blog mentioning that basically an average request on
ChatGPT has a low use,
[QUENTIN]
very low energy, more or less, I'm not sure now, but one minute
of the
[QUENTIN]
oven, that is all these comparisons, like, yeah, some, something
drive your car.
[DOROTHEA]
It's worse than asking ChatGPT if you, you know, whatever. All
the, like, comparing Apple
[DOROTHEA]
and oranges is like one of the favorite disciplines of people in
the field. Yeah.
[DOROTHEA]
I must say, you know, again, I'm not an engineer. So now Sam
Altman said
[DOROTHEA]
it's, it's 0.37 kilowatts, you know, one query. But then again,
you know, the methodological
[DOROTHEA]
discussions start, oh, this is only for text. He didn't talk
about image generation. And,
[DOROTHEA]
and you know what, if you multiply it by billions of times, of
course you
[DOROTHEA]
can say, oh, One query with ChatGPT is much, much better or less
worse than
[DOROTHEA]
driving my car 10 kilometers. But, you know, it's, it's a scale
that accounts for
[DOROTHEA]
it. I think the problem is that the coincidence, the fact that at
a time
[DOROTHEA]
when, let's say in 2020 or like, yeah, when the pandemic hit, et
cetera, we
[DOROTHEA]
were on a path where there seemed to be some consensus that, you
know, climate
[DOROTHEA]
change is an issue that we should tackle and we need, you know,
become more
[DOROTHEA]
energy efficient, we need to have renewable energies. And then
suddenly several things happen. One
[DOROTHEA]
of them being generative AI pops up and is so energy intense that
it threatens
[DOROTHEA]
the transformation, the energy transformation. And that
generative AI or transform models, like the big
[DOROTHEA]
AI models, they are responsible for data centers in areas with
water stress, where the
[DOROTHEA]
data centers consume a lot of water and a lot of electricity,
etc. And that's
[DOROTHEA]
just. It couldn't have come at a worse time because just at a
time when
[DOROTHEA]
we kind of agreed that, you know, we should move towards
renewables, et cetera, this
[DOROTHEA]
pops up. And it's also very interesting from business ethics
point of view, to see
[DOROTHEA]
the change in the tech industry, as you said at the beginning of
this podcast,
[DOROTHEA]
how the CEOs from Big Tech lined up at Trump's inauguration a few
years before.
[DOROTHEA]
They were like, saying things like, Microsoft would say, we are
becoming carbon negative by
[DOROTHEA]
2030, we will remove all historical emissions since 1975. And
then they partially bought OpenAI,
[DOROTHEA]
and now they're falling behind their climate targets. And what
for, you know, if, if
[DOROTHEA]
the kind of AI that OpenAI develops at least was the same kind of
AI
[DOROTHEA]
that can help us tackle climate change issues then it would be
fair. But the
[DOROTHEA]
kind of AI that OpenAI develops is mostly used for Ghibli fraud,
for you know,
[DOROTHEA]
fake chat or fake cat videos or deep fake porn, whatever, you
know, that's consuming
[DOROTHEA]
energy. Whereas potential solutions to climate change issues
probably come from far less energy intense
[DOROTHEA]
models. And this is, I don't know, I can't get my head around
that and
[DOROTHEA]
how we try to absolve ourselves from the responsibility one query
only uses, you know
[DOROTHEA]
that and that much and well,
I won't use my car today so I can spend my day on chat GPT
[DOROTHEA]
with a good conscience. That's just ridiculous. It's. We really
need to think about that.
[QUENTIN]
And, and basically you point exactly to the direction why it's
also very complex to
[QUENTIN]
answer these questions because in the narrative of AGI, one of
the arguments connected to
[QUENTIN]
sustainability is the following. What if it can helps to solve
cancer or, or climate
[QUENTIN]
change? Because you find the solutions with these tools, what is
the cost you're ready
[QUENTIN]
to pay to basically solve these issues? Which is. It's a very
difficult question to
[QUENTIN]
to answer because you have a lot of uncertainty the capacity of
these tools to
[QUENTIN]
reach this goal and seconds when and if, if it will be capable of
doing
[QUENTIN]
this. So then you investing with a lot of uncertainty. But that
being said, it's
[QUENTIN]
still true that we use these tools in scientific research
extensively. If it's helping or
[QUENTIN]
not, we can leave it open here and hopefully it has at least both
effects.
[QUENTIN]
In some situation might help, in other it might be destructive.
But then basically it
[QUENTIN]
leads to the right concept comparison and I think that's the
hardest because indeed you
[QUENTIN]
create some new needs and energy spending like giblification.
Everybody create these images that are
[QUENTIN]
energy consuming using water and that maybe people who have done
other activities less harmful
[QUENTIN]
to the environment without I'm not sure. But when it comes to
work and also
[QUENTIN]
how we substitute some actions and gain in some situation
productivity, we still have this
[QUENTIN]
question what will be the static code without Genai, without AI
in general? What will
[QUENTIN]
be the action the human will take and will it be more or less
harmful
[QUENTIN]
to the environment because humans are polluting, right? And if I
think that I have
[QUENTIN]
to, I don't know, write a report doing research on Google,
writing and writing and
[QUENTIN]
writing on my computer and taking days. If I can be a bit more
efficient
[QUENTIN]
with Gen AI spending more energy but for shorter amount of time
it's difficult for
[QUENTIN]
me to wrap my head around this. So that's why I still struggle to
fully
[QUENTIN]
have a position on this for sure. You see the data centers they
suggest to
[QUENTIN]
create
nuclear facilities next door just to fuel with LGDs. So for sure
it's, it's, it's
[QUENTIN]
a massive. And I, I agree that reducing to the average cost of a
request
[QUENTIN]
is really misleading because you have complex, more or less
complex requests and also vastly
[QUENTIN]
different type of usage. Some that are relatively useless to
compared to other that might
[QUENTIN]
help to do scientific research. And we can, we can also debate if
actually art
[QUENTIN]
on no, not art but just joking and create these things are, is
useless or
[QUENTIN]
not. But well just overall as you can see, I'm a bit puzzled by
this
[QUENTIN]
question. I'm not sure.
[DOROTHEA]
Yeah, same same. I mean I'm hoping, you know, I'm hoping it's
true. I'm, I'm
[DOROTHEA]
hoping that it pays off. I'm hoping that this is, you know,
what's going to
[DOROTHEA]
happen, that we're having a breakthrough. But still, as I said a
few minutes ago,
[DOROTHEA]
it takes humans to cooperate. Even if AI finds a puzzling
solution to cancer or
[DOROTHEA]
you know, climate change, whatever, are we willing to accept that
or is the, you
[DOROTHEA]
know, we also have an oil industry and fossil interests that are
not in favor
[DOROTHEA]
of that. So.
[QUENTIN]
Yeah, so what will be your advice at the individual level already
for people who
[QUENTIN]
want to interact with Genai in a more ethical way?
[DOROTHEA]
Use it carefully. Well, I mean what can I say? You can choose the
provider.
[DOROTHEA]
We do have European alternatives now with Lucia like the, the
French, France based AI.
[DOROTHEA]
So if you have some geopolitical issues and if you, you know,
care about these
[DOROTHEA]
topics, you have European alternatives. You know, make sure that
you never copy paste, make
[DOROTHEA]
sure that you, you know, keep your brain in the loop. But you
know, as
[DOROTHEA]
I said in the beginning, it's yeah, all the educational advice is
very difficult to
[DOROTHEA]
give and I'm also still figuring out how to use it best myself.
Haven't resolved
[DOROTHEA]
that yet.
[QUENTIN]
And for businesses, will you have also advices or things for
businesses?
[DOROTHEA]
I think you know, your, the way how you handle AI, where you use
it,
[DOROTHEA]
how you use it is part of your overall non financial
responsibility. Just as you
[DOROTHEA]
address your environmental responsibility, your social
responsibility, you have a technological responsibility, make
sure you
[DOROTHEA]
include AI into your materiality assessments. Is this where do we
have an impact with
[DOROTHEA]
our use of AI, what are the risks, etc. You know, just deal with
it
[DOROTHEA]
like one of the other issues that you have already had to
incorporate into your
[DOROTHEA]
non financial responsibility strategies.
[QUENTIN]
And one very last question that I love to ask to close the
podcast. Are
[QUENTIN]
you more hopeful or fearful about the future with AI?
[DOROTHEA]
Can I say I'm Swiss, I'm neutral?
I don't know. I don't know. It's really difficult because it's on
so many levels.
[DOROTHEA]
On a personal level, I think for, for me, you know, I, I might be
one of those who benefit. I don't feel threatened, but on a, on a
global
[DOROTHEA]
scale, it looks different. So I can't really have one answer to
that question. It
[DOROTHEA]
really depends on whose perspectives I might benefit, I guess, or
overall, I, I'm not
[DOROTHEA]
threatened by it, but for other people it looks different. And
we, as we said
[DOROTHEA]
with the Sustainable Development Goals, we said we leave no one
behind. And I think,
[DOROTHEA]
you know, the same has to be, you know, applied to AI. We need to
make sure that we don't just cut off people who never had a
chance to
[DOROTHEA]
even acquire skills and leave them behind.